Welcome to all the legends out there listening to the Naval podcast, the number one podcast in the universe and your authoritative source for new knowledge. We've got three founders with us here today. On my right is Gary Tan from Y Combinator. They say it's the most reliable way to become a billionaire is to join the Y Combinator program and then start as a trillionaire. That's one way to do it.
We're all drinking by the way except one person who's not drinking. You have to figure out the Russian roulette. It's actually sober. And then on my left I've got Daniel from Able Police. They started off by turning body cam footage into police reports but now they have a whole set of tools for compliant AI chat.
translation, what else do you guys do? Citizen reporting, all kinds of things. Okay. Then on my right, I've got Farbood from ALIS, the health super app. As usual, we don't really care about what these guys are building. We care more about what they're learning about building, what they're figuring out, what they're still trying to figure out, and the principles that they can share with other founders. So, does anyone have anything they want to jump in with? I mean, the topic that everyone's thinking about right now is AI, right?
AI yeah, I think I've heard something about it Yeah, I kind of hate talking about it because it's the most perishable thing like you know the podcast will be obsolete by the time it ships But it's still also the most interesting because it's the fastest changing thing in the environment that's high impact So it's the steepest learning curve and you're always trying to trade notes with people to kind of see where they're at In fact, that was that a thing with you recently where I bumped into you and the conversation really turns to AI of course Yeah, so we can avoid it for a little while, but I feel like we'll circle back on that topic. I got a question for
you, what are you being floored by at YC in terms of what you see the companies doing with AI? I think the awkward thing is I basically slept three hours a night for four months and then somehow went from not coding at all to basically teaching people how to do it and making one of the top 100 open source packages for how people vibe code called GStack.
is very, very weird. And now, like at some point I met Pedro from Brex. And then after that, I basically converted from like cloud code, like cult to open cloud cult within like 24 hours. And then now we use both. But like, it seems like basically if you, you know, the craziest idea that I discovered is that if you're just willing to spend like $100,000 a year on tokens, you can basically live like you are a normal citizen in 2028.
Like it's just pretty clear that token cost is going to come down. Compute is going to go way, way up. Like, you know, we think like 90,000 X or so there will be 90,000 X the amount of like inference from here to like three years from now. You plot it out in some curve. Yeah. 90,000 times. I mean, it's like many, many orders of magnitude. Which is going to baked in both with the chips and data centers are building out. Yeah. I mean, you know, a lot of people say that Nvidia is way.
Overpriced but what if it's way way underpriced by like several orders of magnitude right now? And then thousand by when I don't know 24 to 36 months Okay, so five orders of magnitude basically yeah, I mean we might be off by a couple orders yeah, yeah I mean I mean it's actually the thing that's crazy is if you go up by five orders of magnitude It's not just what it does in terms of usage but in terms of capabilities because every order of magnitude you go up new capabilities emerge and you know, I've been
I've been pretty behind the curve on AI for a while. Like I missed it in 2020 to 2022 because you know, I'd grown up my whole life hearing about AI from when I was doing CS and Just assumed it was one of those things like fusion that was never gonna come and then it came. Yeah when it came it came really fast and at first a lot of the stuff people were saying about it sounded breathless and like they were talking their own book Yeah, but it seemed crazy. They turned out to be right so far, right? It's not so I think the the big there were many big questions about AI coming up, right now I think the the
like one question I used to have in my mind is like, is it going to be distributed or is it going to be centralized? And now that's kind of morphed into like, is open source going to be good enough for most use cases or are you always going to need the frontier proprietary models? There's the whole thing about like, it's weird that China is making all the open source stuff and the US is doing all the closed source stuff. And so where do we go from there? There's the question of, is it going to be nationalized or is it going to be sort of private sector?
Especially if you're saying, hey, it's a new Manhattan project. These are the new nuclear weapons. Then like private companies building them and controlling them. Doesn't make sense. But I think the most interesting remaining question, there's still one that I really care about over the others where there's no clear answer yet, is I think the people in the labs believe that the scaling laws are such that the AIs will keep getting smarter until they become smarter than the smartest humans.
probably through the process of recursive self-intelligence, recursive improvement, but they call ASI. And I think that is the big question. So two years ago, you could have taken the viewpoint that AI will get you mid at everything, but it's not going to be the pro at anything. Now you're getting to the point where it'll get you the pro at everything, but we don't know if it'll get you the last creative mile, like that last bit of moving out of the system and creating something new, not just recombining what's already in the training sets.
Progress that it made on the Airdish math problem bother you it bothers me for sure. I mean that bothers me. It's a proper discovery I don't be bothered by laws of the universe right so bothered me definitely surprises But at the same time I still don't see like broad general creativity, but anyway, that's separate I was a math major and I really loved proofs and Something actually making progress in that domain in a meaningful way that looks really original Like there's something creepy about it almost like but it was directed by someone right sure
So, and I think that's fine. But everyone was surprised who was involved. Right, right. Like, I don't know if you saw the interview. I guess all that stuff is kind of like boring. It just means like, go do something else. Like, if you have limited time to think about something, do you want to spend it opining over the fact that there's a machine that's better than a human that's something now, or just go apply your humaneness to something that you haven't thought about? Or actually, to riff on Gary's point, are we going to end up in a place where a machine is strictly better than a machine with a human?
Like a human in the loop doesn't add anything. That's the biggest question, right? Like because chess went that way. I hope not. There was Centaur chess. Somebody was telling me about this, but there was Centaur chess where like the chess computer plus the human would beat just a chess computer, but eventually just the computer alone beat the Centaur model. I guess for me, I'm dealing with AI in the most practical way humanly possible, you know, speeding up.
thousands of agents for people on demand, build a massive fleet management system, an eval harness. The reality of it is like, I don't think intelligence is the bottleneck, cost is the bottleneck. Right now. Right now, when we started doing it, every single person in our app has their own open claw running for them. Oh, same. It's a really powerful way. For health.
Yeah. Oh my god. Like mine wrote an entire... But what about this open claw then? What's that? People just want open claw right now. No, but it's not open claw anymore because when we started with open claw and opus, it was $100 a month per person. We spent three, four months driving that down to $2.84. Do you use pie now? We built an entire stack that is just completely wild that has an eval harness.
And then is like an entire egentic fleet that can spin up and down elastic so that I deal with the mundane parts of that stuff all the time I still think what's way more interesting is to think about what humans will do when they don't have to do these things but I think that there is a very real phenomenon going on right now
where the people who would know the most in the labs are basically saying there will be nothing left for humans to do. Really, when you when you read the lines of what they're saying, they're saying in different ways, but they're saying your harness doesn't matter because within a year the AI will be spinning up harnesses as needed. And you won't even be the consumer because it'll be talking to other AIs and beyond the orders problem, it will be solving fundamental problems of material science and physics and math and engineering and health. Great.
Yes, but then you know that's taking the average person out on the street working them up into a frenzy They're getting angry and scared because fear is a precursor I'm afraid of anger try to get all my friends to go work at Anthropic so then I'll have lots of friends there who will get me into the Anthropic level 2 breadline Yeah, right now I feel like pretty solidly in level 3 There's only two jobs alright. It'll be an anthropic employee and sex worker for an anthropic employees alright. Oh, I mean that's
The scary part right that's the one and it's getting people worked up and the real world consequences of that because you don't live alone you you live inside a hundred thundering herd called humanity and if that thundering herd decides to like go left towards a cliff because it's mad or because enraged because poison you're gonna go with it you know you're not gonna be the lone bison sitting out there by yourself on the edge so Naturalization right like that's where it would go you know but right now that you can see that trans starting with their attacking data centers right they're attacking data centers
That's just stupid. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
It's a rational response, but it's an irrational carrier. So they're saying it's because of water. It's not about water. That was a lie that was debunked. Yeah, it's not about reason. I mean, it's like socialism. It's not about reason. It's about how you get the people going. You're getting poor and you want more money. Or in this case, you're feeling threatened. It's like all in the city right now. Like you're going to be replaced and you want to stop this train. You want to be like, I want on this train. At all points, that's rational. I want to be on this train. Yeah, that's rational. Totally rational. So in this case, this is a case of especially when you have the popular delusions of the madness of
crowds you have the ends justify the means. So in this case the water is just a means. If I find another one, if it wasn't water, there'd be some endangered egret, some bird, some snail. Are they right? Well they can't stop it. This technology is a genie. That's what the genie... I don't think that's true. There's been times in the past where like, yeah, like smashing, like spinning looms actually stopped the revolution. Very briefly. And it slowed it down. There was other technologies. But we have spinning looms now.
Of course, but there's other technologies where they refused to issue a patent or something so it became unmarketable because it was just politically going to be too difficult. I think that basically we ingest 100 years ago 50% of the labor force in the US was working on farms. And that's no longer true.
Right and now it's great. Now it's a great thing. Now it's 2% working on a farm. We don't have 48% unemployment. Yeah, thank you. We don't have 48% unemployment and we all have food, right? The question is what is the speed of transition? The speed of transition is a problem, right? That one took like 60 or 70 years. Yeah, okay. This one is going to be much faster. Have you ever worked at a Fortune 500 company? Those things are so stupid. Nobody has.
Oh, yes. I worked in Microsoft for two years. No, no, I mean like nobody there works. Yes, exactly. It's already all make work jobs anyway, right? It's like how much of the population is working and then how much of that is working for the private sector and then how much of that is not working in some bullshit job. Graber was right. Yeah, very few people are actually working.
I mean I'm working more because of AI. I got six codex agents running all the time. I agree. I'm working the hardest I've ever worked because of AI. And so I just kind of think people are going to work more. The productivity is way higher. The leverage is way higher. But that's all true until AI can totally and completely replace you, which I don't see around the corner, but I'm more open-minded about it now. I don't know how you do the house. I used to think that was an impossibility. I used to be bearish on that. Now I'm like...
Well, no, I gotta pay attention. That's exactly my philosophy. It's like you have to come to company company B You have the same technology everyone has access like you know, hopefully everyone has well that's the key So are we gonna is it gonna be open source right or is gonna be great right because right now if they keep scare mongering some of that might be well now You need national approval We just saw Sam Alman said that codex 5.6 will be rolled out slowly to partners approved by the US government first my god So he's already cooperating because he doesn't want to get shut down like anthropic. Yes
And so it's already starting and so then a small number of people it's become the defense department thing Then it's like who has access who has control, you know, they have cyber weapons Maybe they get to hack the side of the systems first. Maybe they get to control them Maybe they get master surveillance that we don't for our own good, right? That's how it always starts. So to me it is definitely
much scarier that a small group of people have control over AI than everybody has it. But everybody having it is also scary because of, well, I mean, there's a printed bio weapon thing, but the bio printer labs are pretty locked down to begin with. I'm not sure how real that is. It was like good chip it. And in fact, it's now coming out, which many of us already knew and been saying for years that the funder and creators of the
coronavirus, COVID-19, were basically the US government and the Chinese government working in Cahoots. It was basically a Fauci and crew in North Carolina. So the joke I tweeted was like, designed by NIH in North Carolina, assembled in China. Right? Because it's like the old Apple line, designed by Apple in California, assembled in China. But that's basically what happened with the coronavirus. They were doing gain of function research to build a vaccine. They were being total cowboys. This is crazy stuff. I mean,
Anyway, I'm not saying IAIS and that's going to lead to bio weapons because to the extent that AI would need to bio weapons right now, you know, some smart biohacker student could already do it, right? So it's not like- Don't kill people. People kill people. It is democratizing a certain capability. I mean, game theory wins out in the end one way or the other. Game theory on this is not good. When mutually shared destruction is available to every individual, the game theory is not good. My point of view is the problems are already out there.
They're already as bad as you're like you're saying that they're going to be like the problems are already out there and like AI is the way and just technology progress in general is the solution to all those problems. Gary can't even afford his open claw that's like reading his email right now. How is he gonna pay for the nuclear bomb claw that we're... No, I'm good. I can pay for it. I just want everyone to pay for it. No, no, no, exactly. I want everyone to be able to pay for it. It's like a hundred thousand dollars a year basically. It's totally worth it. If you hire a person...
you can afford your open claw. People have gotten so, I don't know, if it's AI psychosis or what it is that at this point I usually just want to be like, can I just talk to your AI please?
Where do I email your AI? I don't need to interact with you because people are like, you can't even text someone and get an answer from them anymore. So many people are writing emails and writing documents of an AI like an X. I see all these posts that are clearly written by it. I'm like, why should I read it? I want my AI to read it. I think that's so clearly. If AI is going to write it, AI should read it. That's totally a lower class signal. Exactly. That's ridiculous. When I get emails that are clearly written in AI, I'm like, dude.
That's the last thing. Well, you can write it better with AI because what you need is a multi-stage voice date. You write with AI, I don't shoot. I sure do, actually. I don't know how you caught me. That's why I keep jumping to the defense. I hate AI writing. It's too verbose. It's too verbose. It's too clinical. But you can fix it.
Like that, you know, we have super intelligence. Why wouldn't just write what's the value of actually reading something and realizing it's written by a person is so much. Yes fair enough. I feel like such a jackass when I'm reading something. You're not writing your own stuff. How are you going to talk? You're going to lose your ability to speak well because good writing and good speaking are the output of good thinking. Yes. And if you're not practicing that muscle. Yeah, I suppose you can do it. My counter argument would be you know how like sometimes you
actually really need like a person. I mean, I don't think this replaces people, but I can have now a high bandwidth conversation with a relatively smart AI model all of the time. And you should do that. You should talk to the AI model all you want. But I'm saying like, when you write something that's meant to be consumed by other humans, if that's written by an AI, that's a disservice to the other human. You're wasting their time. Everything the AI wrote should instead be compressed down by you or you should really
Like take the time to make the point as succinctly as possible to get a person to respect their time. Otherwise their AI is going to end up reading your AI and Neither of you are in the loop. You're not even this is one reason I enjoy Twitter less lately is because I think in the future people will just have really really impressive skill files that actually extract like the style and the diction and
Like, I mean, the thing about, the thing that people underestimate that I've learned with some of the stuff is that you can just have more and more evals. Like you're saying you have an eval harness, right? Like, you can have multiple levels. You can have cross modal evals. And when you have enough, like sort of, I mean, it's crosstalk, but if you do enough of it, like you can actually improve the skill file to a point where it's indistinguishable. And like, this is without...
the next level of model like imagine fable 7 fable 8 like you will not be able to tell i guarantee yeah no it's obviously gonna get there less than nine months like you like this whole ai writing conversation will fucking go away i think i'm still a little better defended and higher up on that hill than you guys because i write very very short and yes they're very bad at summarizing but also very bad at distilling good writing is novelty yeah like it's like unexpected and anything that is guessing a next token from a regression can't do it yeah
It's not totally true. It won't do something original. If you like co-write with an AI or use it as an editor to bounce ideas off, almost always it'll have like this one short, it's always like a short-turner phrase, but you're like, oh, that's good. And it got that from somewhere else on the internet, but the internet's a big place. Actually, I programmed a really crazy thing in Gbrain. It's the retrieval thing I made. It's actually basically a collider of different vector spaces.
And so, I mean, and this is the kind, what I mean by like, boil the ocean, like these are things you can do now. Like, it has my whole corpus of like everything I've ever said, all my emails, all my slacks, all my text messages, my DMs, everything. And then, so I actually have like, like 400,000 markdown files on like literally anything I've ever thought or read at this point. And then I have this thing called LSD mode, which is a lateral, shit, what's the S?
less as an inc. Sorry, lateral stochastic drift. I mean, I just wanted to call it L-STEMO. Yeah, of course. I was trying to remember the chemical composition. Yeah. But basically, it's take every possible vector space that is not pointed in the same direction and then cross them and then do a ranking, a re-ranking across all of these ideas. And you can actually more like it's called brainstorm L-STEMO and it just like finds bangers.
And sometimes if I just am bored, sometimes I'll just be like, give me some LSD bangers. And it will literally give me like 10 or 20 ideas that like, three or four different frontier models have actually re-ranked and said like, actually, if you look at this, and we cross-reference against like Exa, actually, this is actually a really good idea. And I'm like, this is finding ideas at like a ridiculous amount of scale. So I mean, I get it, but.
I'm also calling bullshit because I think that like this is just the classic and I think this is actually a really fun thing that is useful. It's um, you know, I think it's like a pulbic idism like the way to you know, build the future is just like live in the future and work backwards, right? And so like it is inevitable that like rather than fucking complain about AI like it's helpful like it scores points like I see it on X like people love to like fucking score points on me. Okay, so this is a problem
It's like I'm fucking a year to it like I don't give a fuck if someone comes to me and is like fuck your AI writing because it's like you know what my AI writing is so fucking good I don't even give a shit. No, I read it like I'm alive. I'm a human being still right but um, anyway, that's how I that's you know
Welcome to my TED Talk. No, I just think that like I just think that like to predict the future to just live in the future, right? Right. That's the best way to learn. And everyone should be AI maxing. Yes. Just to figure it out. Otherwise, you're going to have no sense of where it's going. I think like today's virtue signal is I mean, I think that it's not helpful to people like there are people who are going to listen to this who want to be rich and they're going to be like, oh no, like I shouldn't use AI to write. Oh, I see. Okay. Yeah. So I mean,
I agree with you that like human beings and like what you really think matters a lot and you should write. Yeah. And then for me that writing process is like actually workshopping
in telegram with my open-vlogs. I would say for me, I don't use A to write. Well, that's not true. I used to write code, so maybe I am contradicting myself. But code is like, it's a utilitarian. It's like, code is meant to be consumed by another computer. It's not meant to be consumed by a human. So if I want to create something that's meant to be consumed by a computer, I will use a computer. But if it's meant to be consumed by a human, then I want to understand the thing. I want to
you know, ruminate, marinate within it and then I want to respect the reader or listener's time and give them that insight and nugget. Now the AI is used for brainstorming. That part I like, I do use AI's to brainstorm. I use them like, give me synonyms for this, give me other ideas associated with this, pull in tangential information. You know, I argue with it sometimes, especially because a lot of them are on guardrails.
But I don't use it to actually create the output that I expect a human to sit there and read. That just seems to me like a discontinuity, right? It's kind of unfair. It's a quality thing. I mean, I agree with you. Like out of box, the quality is bad. Yeah. But you can have like 2028 level stuff. I mean, like I think the pattern that I'm trying to like, you know, tell people is that like, yes, like AI writing out of the box sucks right now. Like if you rely on it out of the box, it sucks.
But if you have an eval harness, if you've actually gone to like build a big enough corpus, if you actually like you've done cross modal eval and like built, you know, a bang, like I have a banger engine, I have a banger gate. I want to see some banger essays from you. Yes. Because I feel like and even if they were from you, essays right now with like a million views. Yeah, they wouldn't even be good enough because you are the president of Y Combinator, right? I want to see someone who's just like out there posting, right?
Using this system, rise up, make an anon account, disconnect it from yourself entirely, then come back and throw it in my face when you get to 300,000 followers. Okay.
because I'd be so curious if you could do that. That would prove it. You could absolutely. Because there are 300,000 people out there who will fall for it. But if you get that, then at least that's something, right? But if you pick a PG or me or someone who's smart and insightful and wants high quality content and knows what that looks like, you're not going to get those people as well. I've never been more creative. And I think something happened probably just in the past few months, especially with Codex. I think I'm way ahead of the curve on Codex.
I'm running my computer from home on my phone here in a way that you can actually do without modifying codex in some ways. And like the amount of creative productivity I have is way higher than it ever was. I think like it's six months ago, 12 months ago, the promise wasn't quite there. And so everyone was like, eh, this AI thing is not that useful. But I think it hit an inflection point in the past few months. Yeah, I think clog code was a typical point.
Yeah, in December 2025 was the tipping point and you had to reevaluate AI. AI had a couple of tipping points. One was diffusion into images, you know, it kind of started at all when you first saw like stability and you were just like, well, okay, made a dog face and you can be like cats and guys on the moon. Yeah, it was wild when it first came out.
And then probably instruct GPT and chat GPT. And then there was another jump with the reasoning models like 01 and 03. But I think the cloud code was a big unlock because it just unlocked a series of practical use cases. Whereas before it was like, okay, it's a better Google search or you know, it's like, this saves me time like doing research or I can learn from this or I can even have a small conversation. But cloud code was a massive unlock. And the big thing here is like this is the worst it'll ever be.
Of course. Yeah, yeah, no it's getting there like so many crypto isms that basically super apply to you could have said that when fable is released and you would have been wrong because they had away from us. Yes, briefly It'll be back use cases. You couldn't tell the difference between fable and mini max For almost so that brings me to a good topic. I do want to discuss these open source versus closed source, right? How good are the open source models? So really? Okay, I haven't tried Geo five times five to ten times less the cost. Yeah
Okay, what should we use them? Minimax is just mind-bendingly good. It needs a good harness though. Yeah, yeah, it doesn't need a good harness, but it's it if you got one it works really well. I was thinking today I'd love to see like take the latest and greatest open source model and they seem to have gone from a 12 month gap to a nine month at six month and now some people are saying three months I don't know if it's weak some people saying three months whatever It is what it is. It's very jagged right and some domains they seem caught up in some domains they don't but
I would love to see someone take the latest and greatest open source model, put it inside a very good harness, give it all the tools, make it available through a beautiful download desktop app and jailbreak it. Strip it of every time it pushes back at you for anything stupid, any tone policing, any other research that I'll just tell you the truth every time and just call it truth.ai.
Like that's all it does. Like I just want to see that. I just want to see what happens. Like because the one place where the frontier, I'll always pay for more intelligence because I'd rather be right more often than wrong because I just think you're high leveraged, right? And obviously I can afford it, but maybe if I was doing some highly repetitive tasks I wouldn't. But as a simple example, like if you're doing something where the AI is right 90, you have one AI that's right.
I saw this stat, like 99.9% of time. And the other ones write 90% of time. Well, if they're recursively looping and you run them 100 times, the one that was right 9% of time is not going to be right 13% of time. Whereas the one that was 99.9 will drop to 80 or 90, right? So.
Intelligence doesn't matter on the margin. Now those numbers are obviously chosen 99.9 versus 90. It's not 99 versus 90. You notice there's 100x lower error rate rather than 100x. Errors accumulate. Errors compound. That's the point. Errors compound. Anyway, going back, I will pay for more intelligence. And I'm not that cost sensitive when it matters of judgment because you're always applying leverage and your time is also very valuable. But what I am curious about is the frontier models do annoy me by constantly trying to railroad me.
you know, they're like, well, I shouldn't be telling you that. How about I give you this other answer that's really messed up? How much of that are they doing? If you talk to it about like serious personal stuff. Yeah.
And it also like always mess up UTC versus like Pacific time and it thinks it's like 7 p.m.. And it thinks it's like 5 a.m.. I was like hey, this is time to go to sleep After a while I was like what is going on with you like it's literally 7 p.m.. And it's like oh sorry like anthropic are like Jeff is me so you know if I'm if you're talking about something serious And I think it's late like you know I would love like a completely jailbroken best of breed
Open source for you. They'll be great. Holy locals find doesn't have to be in a nice package. It doesn't have to be local actually What are you doing where the jailbreak is so important because I'm like well there are a couple of things where it does stop you or catch your track right you see that right there a whole bunch where you don't see it where it is successfully keeping you away from whatever you want to know I'm doing always a switch to GLM 5.2, and it'll just do it now, but if you go ask if any question about race gender immigration mental health doctor advice legal advice
So I guess I don't know why you need a harness for this right like for me I'm using harness to the music agents because it's going out and doing things I have to say harness to the just I just want to learn this does my harness I just mean like I want it maxed out I don't want any excuse for like why my open source model is even slightly worse than it could be I wanted operating I want the best open source model configured in the best way and it just tells me the truth all the time because I used to go to grok for that but even grok is a little neutered Yeah, it's not like one's talked about this
Is he? People pointed out like someone by it. He was like, oh geez. And we wanted it to just be real and it was giving neoliberal answers. I'm dying to talk about what you said the other day, but I also don't know if you want to say it publicly. The entire, like everything's probably hacked. It's priority hacked. Oh no, I'll talk about it. So the question is like where are the open source models catching up? Right. And so there's a couple of different theories and I'll just lay out the theories that I know and the evidence for them, but I don't have a
point of view yet. I mean it's possible that these are true. So there's some of it that's obviously, you know, the Chinese are doing their own pre-training. They have their own compute. They have their own data sets. In fact, they can crawl more the data sets because they're less bound by copyright laws, right? They can crawl YouTube and Reddit and all that stuff.
And they train these models. That's like the base model, right? Then there's like the accusations that Anthropic made, which they're distilling our models, which is they're taking, they're querying our models and mass, taking that data user training model. I mean, if I were China, that's what I would do. For sure. And thus creating a jagged intelligence kind of model. And definitely some of that is going on, but I think it's rich of Anthropic to call that out when Anthropic crawled the open web and distilled the open web. That's all these AIs are, right? In fact, one.
platform that I think would be very popular if the government were to do it is to say, hey, you guys have, since you trained on the open web, if you trained on the open web and open data, you have to open your model after X months, after 12 months or something, right? That seems to be like a pretty fair thing to say, especially like open AI, you have to be, otherwise you have to be actually open AI, right? An anthropic, you're the one talking doom and gloom and you're building God, but you're not gonna keep God in the leash for yourself, Dario. We don't want like a priest.
you know, controlling God for the rest of us interpreting the Bible for the rest of time. So I think that would be popular. Okay, so anyway, number one, they are, they are, they have their own pre-training, but they get the full corpus of the web. They don't have to obey any copyright laws, right? Second, they are distilling the existing American models, which are starting to get more locked down. And a lot of this government nationalization control helps them be locked down. But you know, there are data brokers online that are taking like, cloud max accounts and reselling tokens from that in an API format to end users like 80%
off because those plans are heavily subsidized for end users. They charge the enterprises. It's like $8,000 a month retail. Anyone who's like run like an exchange or a regulated online brokerage knows that KYC is a dime a dozen. People get back KYC all the time. They're like print passports in Vietnam if you want, right? Yeah, exactly. So I think the distillation is going to be hard to stop. But I think the biggest one to think about, and there's some genuine algorithmic breakthroughs like the DeepSeq paper. Oh, yeah. DeepSeq R1.
incredible systems people very very smart people and I would guess just by looking at the numbers of resumes and so on that the majority
of mathematicians and researchers in AI today are Chinese. Like they produce more STEM graduates, more PhDs in the relevant fields, more Olympiad winners than anybody else, right? And then a lot of the US staff is Chinese. So in fact, that's why I tweeted like AI is our Chinese against their Chinese, right? And these guys, and I don't think there's any conspiracy required. These guys are all just friends, you know, they live in the same dorms, they went to the same schools, they live in the same buildings and apartments, they hang out. Yeah, and they switch jobs like crazy. And not just the Chinese.
you see everyone's hopping from lab to lab to lab and they're just taking data with them. Okay, so there's all of that going on, right? But then on top of it, I don't think that the AI companies have the security profile of a top US national secure compartment facility, right? They do not know how to protect secrets. So of course they're getting hacked. Of course the weights are getting leaked. And if you're Chinese or anybody else, you're not gonna like just
take the buates and release them back, you're going to use that to distill at high speed and train your own model, right? Or to augment your model. So I think there's another whole system right there that's going on. And the last one, actually, I think the biggest one is none of those. I think no conspiracy is required for the following. If you look at where China is, they're like, okay, we're behind. They've always been behind in software. The US has been way ahead in software. And being ahead in software allows you to extract all the margins because for the longest time, VC has never invested in hardware. Why? Because hardware is a commodity business.
Right? And software had the network effects to lock in software's art as Patrick Coleson said it locks you in. And so people want to invest in software. So even in the US, whenever you get a hardware company funded, the VCs will ask you, well, what's the software lock in? What's the software piece? Right? And so this is why I say hardware is the mode that buys you time to build a software castle.
Right? But guess what? Claude Code burned software down. Software was eating the world and AI ate software. So now software is commoditized. The moment you can specify it and AI can one shot or two shot it or get to it within a couple of shots. I see one from like 5% to about 25%.
hardware 20 to 25 percent hardware but hardware is also commoditized by China any hardware I can make here you can make in China more cheaply and more easily the whole ecosystem is there Shenzhen has like 3000 manufactured this tiny little cable on one little area thanks Nielsen for normalizing relations with China and taking us off the dollar stand yeah and so it's a bringing reshoring manufacturing back to the US is going to take a full generation it should be done no question a big fan of American manufacturing but it's going to take a long time in the meantime
China outproduces every one of the supply chains because they realize there are scale economies in production. So they subsidize the thing upfront, then they become the global supplier. They drive everybody else out of business. And then they control the whole supply chain across these critical industries. So they own hardware. No one's going to be China on hardware in the next decade. It'll ramp up. We'll fight on a bunch of fronts.
They own hardware. So they like the commoditization of software. So when software is getting commoditized, that helps China. So if you're the Chinese government, you're basically funding all these labs. You're doing kind of a public-private partnership where you're saying, don't worry, you don't have to make money. You can be number two or number three. Just open it so the other labs can learn from you and we can catch up and keep up. And if the software is commoditized, then we win on the hardware. So the way I think about it today is that hardware is commoditized.
but it's owned by China for the most part. There's some few exceptions like SpaceX in the US. Software is commoditized. So what's not commoditized? It's actually just AI research. Developing, working on AI itself is the new software engineering. The problem with that is the software used to be democratized. Everyone could compete. John Carmack and John Romero sitting there with a small team could code up Doom and Quake and compete against EA and Activision and so on.
Can't do that in AI. AI takes massive resources, huge GPU clusters, small numbers of research, massive data sets, proprietary data sets.
So in that and then now regulatory capture. So it seems like all the value all the choke points are going into AI and that's controlled by a very small number of companies and ironically the only thing keeping is afloat is a Chinese government subsidizing the whole thing on open source so that their hard work can stay competitive. Yeah, I think the plus they had the weights. They might use that as I mean you can sneak about a one USB stick. You're telling me that already been done.
One person on the inside like there's so many people by the way every male AI founders walking around with a beautiful Chinese girlfriend Have we talked about that like no one talks about that go walk outside Silicon Valley right? I think we all come from a world where advantages like had some durability and you could actually operationalize your advantage against the rest of the world But that's just like narrowing down in time So you know you might have the smartest model But what are you gonna do with it in two weeks in three four weeks when till somebody else has it too so the
I think there's a different part of the game theory that we've not experienced before, which is the time contraction of any of these advantages. And I don't think it makes it harder to predict who's gonna be in charge of anything because, like you said, a few months later, the smartest model is now open source. Guys, I'm so fucking worried.
This is one of my tweets I'm proud of a couple of years back. I said soon everybody will have AI anxiety. Like we're all feeling it. We're all feeling AI anxious. It's incredibly... Oh, I'm jubilant. I am AI jubilant. Yeah, I'm jubilant. But it's both. The anxiety in this good form is kind of fomo-ish, which is like, look at all the great things I can do. I'm AI secure. Don't worry about me, guys. Yeah, but everyone I know that's working up front here a lot, but I'm these things that are researchers, they're depressed. They are.
They're stressed out because I think it's gonna kill us all. That's because they're culture is the first ones I met in 2021 were saying to me that they were putting off having kids or thinking about not having kids because they were afraid for the kids future and I was like, what are you talking about? As opposed to every other time in human history when people were not we're never afraid of their kids future and so they didn't have any kids. Wait, so why is this not just gonna result in Star Trek the next generation? Like that's that's my hope. So the bullshit part of the end of scarcity would be great. The bullshit part about Star Trek the next generation is that they
have AGI clearly, but that AGI is somehow not running things. I mean they couldn't conceive of it yet, right? They have the holodeck, but somehow people are still doing it. It's not that good enough a writer. They're not just living in the holodeck. There's plenty of science fiction that's, you know, bothered to see that idea further through. I mean, it's some large percentage of the San Francisco population has been one-shotted by fentanyl. You don't think the holodeck will take out the rest? Right, right. They just don't show that on the show. Like Gene Roddenberry, like I'm sure he conceived of it. Yeah, yeah, yeah. And it should be too much of a bummer to show like these giant holodeck
You say this and you're living in Star Trek and you're happy. That's true. You're excited for it. But yes, you recognize there's a ton of terrible things that are going to happen. Right. And you're just like, ugh.
It wasn't in Star Trek. Well, it's in there. But to Gary's defense, there's been so much of this electricity. That was a big one, right? Railroads, the cars, these were big, big changes. You used to have to ride a horse. The pony express, do you remember that? That was insane. And people made it. But the more rapid the change, the more influential the displace, the more tumultuous it was. And so now we're having a very rapid change.
We're displacing white collar, we're displacing government, we're displacing managers, we're displacing academics, we're displacing journalists. You know, I learned more from AI than I did in my college for classes. Because I can sit there and I can have it meet me at my exact level of knots. Because they give that to me visually, give me a graph about that.
I can ask dumb questions. I don't understand that. Explain it again. Explain it again. Explain it in a third different way. Explain it visually. Explain it audibly. Explain it with dancing elves. I don't care. Just to keep going over until I get it. I could not do that in class. I can learn so much better. I just have to care. If I care, I can learn anything better than with any tutor, better than with any teacher. So all the people are obsolete and they're going to lead a revolution. Those people need to want more things.
And if you want more things, everyone wants more things. And then if you have this tool and you're not averse to using it, this is why I'm so against like, sorry to bring up the AI writing thing again, but like, I understand like, that makes sense humans. And like, there is a disrespectful aspect when you do bad writing, right? But like that presupposes that like,
the AI can't write well with human beings. That's a fair point because right now the writing is voluminous. It's bad. It takes a little thing like prompt you give it. Okay, but here's the thing. You're giving it a prompt, right? Yes. Why don't you just send me the prompt?
Why do I need to read all the garbage? Because it has to draw on all of human experience. Just give me the prompt. I'll send it to my AI. I have my codex put together a markdown file that I send to my developers that they can give to their cloud code to go execute some things that I want. Don't talk to me. Have your agent talk to my agent. That's literally what it is. My thing will just file an issue on your GitHub repo and then...
I want to get on the zoom and I'm on the zoom having a conversation and then ten minutes in I know this is not for me Yeah, and then I just hit a button and the agent takes over agent of all keeps talking and I go after the next one. Yeah, I swipe right on you
But for all but then the jokes I'm making because you were never there to begin with I think it's time for politics politics Soundly it's been politics most of the most of the time. All right fear mongering politics doesn't matter because of AI You know, that's not what are you talking about? Everything's gonna end nothing. That's like politically relevant right now is gonna be relevant in three years I will say that I was gonna get I wish I could vote for an AI their job I wish I could vote for an AI to represent us
But who's AI? Gary will make it. Somebody can make it. They can open source it. They can put the weights out for us to take a look at. You can read the weights. You can look at the weights. I mean, not personally.
That way it looks often. But like a fully transparent AI that is running first. There's nothing. They had this thing, a whole field called mechanistic interpretability, where they're trying to figure out how the AI thinks and they've like made very little progress. Oh sure. I'm not saying we're going to know, but I'm just saying you have the access to the same thing with AI. By the way, it's an anachronism, our training data.
is a natural language and in computer languages that humans can read and write. And so the AI's are trained on that. But in the future, the AI's will develop their own languages. They'll communicate with each other in some kind of a binary high-speed protocol. They'll almost be talking compiled code or maybe even something completely different that we can't even imagine, which will be more efficient for communication. It's only humans who demand eligibility, but the AI's don't really have it. And part of what makes AI systems so much better than
human coded expert systems is that they don't have to be legible so they can find correlations and patterns that we cannot articulate. In fact, even most of our knowledge is inarticulatable. Most of your feelings are inarticulatable.
You don't even know half the time what you're feeling or thinking. You're not even... You're not even able to talk about our feelings. Yeah, yeah, let's do that. We're experts in that. One place where we are experts. GLM 5.2. I'll vote for GLM 5.2 for office. Yeah, they're Chinese overlords. Hey, it's my favorite distillation of fable. I really do appreciate how the Chinese are making all the open source models out there. It's kind of pathetic that the US just... The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The global economy will appreciate it. The
So that's an interesting point about open source. In some cases now open source is number one. And at least historically, like if you look at things like Linux or other open source projects, once something open source kind of gets in the lead, it really surrenders it. And that's because an ecosystem springs up around it where everyone starts plugging into, especially in enterprise use cases. So right now, Claude and Codex are like slightly ahead of GLM, fable and maybe a lot ahead of GLM.
If something like a GLM, wherever it is surpassed them, it's not clear they'd get a lead back. I mean, because how can you rationalize your limited resources at a company going into something that open sources is winning at? You have to do something with your resources and failing to catch up to open source with your precious resources is not a good use of them. You'd have a clock. Like, so if you're open air and thropic, you would have a certain amount of revenue and money and cash in the bank and investor.
backing and you would have to use that to sort of jump meaningfully ahead of the open source and take the lead again before that runs out. So that's it because like if you look at the AI race, you know, two years ago people thought that Google and Elon and and meta were also competitors. Yeah, there are five kings. There are five kings. There's two kings now. There's two kings. And why is that? Well, it's not just because those guys have the best models. Open AI and and Propic are the only ones that are a making revenue off of their models directly.
And so they're not subsidizing, cross subsidizing from other business. They're not running out of cash. They're actually pouring the cash back in. And the second is because they have very active user basis and now a lot of the improvement is coming through reinforcement learning. They're getting the guidance and the trajectories to improve the models. And so they're just pulling away. And maybe Elon, because he took SpaceX public and he's got that war chest, he gets maybe one more bite at the apple. Plus he's got the data centers in space, so you know, don't bet against Elon. Google, I think, has lost it.
That's quite sad. I never really amazing when I was always like bearish on Google I was tweeting some pretty anti-google management stuff back in the day Where I was like I will know they're serious about AI when I 3.1 pro was the moment that was That was it was no, but it wasn't like it was my pro was better
It wasn't good enough. They never even got the basic app working. I remember I tried to upgrade to pay them $20 a month. It was a nightmare. This huge run around. No, you need to be part of Google One. No, no, you need Google Workspace account. They were first to have contact-inducing usable contacts. Yeah, very cool. And then every time, even today, the iOS app, which I know it's not their platform, but everyone else seems to have figured it out, you put a query into Gemini, you background, it always loses the connection. It just drops it. All the others will just run in the background. How hard is that? It's 2026, run a background app guy.
GRPC just need a little bit more sparta over there meta might be too much I think it's too late for it. I think they have to kill 5,000 Google PMs Like that's the only way it's PM slop the whole he's PM slop at this point, right? Yeah, anywhere you go. It's just like
Tons of products overlapping. It's a huge mess. You can't figure it way through the mail. Some incentive problem now. All the best people want stock in open iron and atropic. Or they want to be sitting alongside the best colleagues in open iron and atropic. Or they want the data set from open iron and atropic. And it certainly don't want to be tied down by all the PMs and all the legacy BS. And they should have replaced Google search with Google AI a long time ago. I don't even look at the results anymore. I just look at Google AI. So here's the alternative vision, which is like Google today could
I mean, they probably have all the transcripts of all the meetings, or if they don't, they should have it. And they have all your emails. Right. And then they probably need to use Anthropic Fable 5 or whatever, because like their own models are not quite good enough. But you could diarize all of these. You could have like...
you know, a markdown file for every single employee at Google. And you can compute a score. Which you've cleverly trade Mark and patented. Google Brain. Google Brain through G-Stack, of course. Are you Google Brain.io? No, anyway. Google Omni is the best for... Google Gary has a price of 7%. It's standard. It's just standard. It's normal. Seriously, you could solve it. Like if someone was a true, like really wanted to fix this.
Like all of these things are just systems problems, right? Yeah, yeah, but it would take it would take larry and surgae walking in there and literally it's like that scene from entourage when arie gold walks back in the office is shooting people like but only with their open clause and live ammunition like i'm serious like You don't they don't need to be there physically like you know one of the things i learned from paedra brex like that's how he runs brex like You know he has total information awareness on like every team and he wouldn't think like the thing that got me didn't didn't they lose to ramp
I mean, hey, I'm kidding. I'm kidding. The rap guys come in. Look, man, I don't have any skin in the game on either of those, okay. We're accepting sponsorships from whoever calls in first. We're paying this more, we'll talk about it. Capital One or anyway, I mean, no, like, I mean, he really did like instrument the CEO brain, like...
For him like it's his personal claw that knows like the KPIs and literally what all of his directs talk about in those meetings and it's significant. He's spying on them all the time. I mean, yes. No, I mean the thing is like I mean, they're not the only company like I've talked to other CEOs They don't publicly talk about this behind closed door. Yeah, this is like the max thing that you could do is like how like concentrate the power in your CEO or co-founding team
So you have actual awareness of what the fuck is going on. Well, the reality is the team should be much smaller. Right. And most of your employees are GPUs working in the data center. I mean, of course, if you can have 10 fewer, like a tenth of your employees right now and just make them the hundred guys, then that's easier said than done. Like most people, most CEOs do not want to fire 50% of the people. But there should be a lot more small companies. I've been on boards where it's like, bro, like we're fucked and we need
to fire 80% of the people and you have a shot like you literally have like tens of millions of dollars in the bank still. Part of the policy you don't know which 80% because you're working through managers. What I'm saying is now you can't. And that's not a little thing. That's a big fucking thing. Like you can have total information. Like okay like this is a big thing to me. I think that the future is essentially that like you need to ride the fucking AGI. Like you actually need to. Like the most significant thing to me is like
The one million token context window is a big deal. It's like, I mean, I talk about it as like three Harry Potter books. But guess what? Like a human being can keep in their brain fucking seven things plus or minus three. Right, right, right. Like we are little monkey brains. Yeah, yeah. Like we talk about like super intelligence is like in the future. Fuck that. Super intelligence right now, like an agent working for you can literally make.
Like a thousand pages like printed valuable useful credible god, let's not talk about a I writing Yeah, I'm not writing. No, it's an idea point, you know, it's like you can understand what the fuck is happening in your work like every CEO in the world Like really so so you could you can have your AI say tying to all the systems in the entire company evaluate everything
Tell me which 20% of fire right now. I mean you could do that and you should that's like the easiest thing in the world We know that no one will do it. No one's doing. We're talking about yeah, I've rejected meta plus. It's not perfect Do you know anything about me? I like only what I read is like I mean half of the smart people I knew at meta have left. Yeah. Yeah, I mean I'm sorry like I really like meta, you know like you guys are great But like it's like a lot of shit. Yeah, I think it's yeah, let's watch up
Well, I don't think you can build a culture or morale by just buying people, especially all different from all different stripes and places and ramming them together. It's then you have no idea how many are actually missionaries, how much are I mean mercenaries culture is a real thing that takes time to evolve and grow. Meta of all places needs to do what I just described, which is like, should you know, someone has to actually know what is actually happening per person per team. And it's I mean, you can do this now, right?
But you also have to tune it. Like, if there has to be a rating, it's like, what is actually a good employee? What is their behavior? What are their characteristics? Like, you can actually tune your culture right now. I mean, it's taking the whole engineering team and turning them into data labelers. It's just like, it's like dropping a nuclear bomb in the place. So that seems indiscriminate to me, right? Like, why would you do that? Especially because you have this incredibly fine grained...
thing. Like you have a prompt, you have a skill file, you have like a bunch of markdown, like you can actually tune it to exactly the output. I think that org is just too large. Yes. It's the same problem as Google. When you have a large org, you do things that actually make sense in certain domains, then it gets leaked to the press, gets sensationalized. Oh, they're turning everyone into data laborers. Probably these have too many people. You have too many cooks in the kitchen. But you need a small... You feel like way less than what you can fit in three Harry Potter books. Yeah. Right? Like...
I mean, I'm sorry to bring that up. I think that's a big deal. The most millennial example you could give. Sorry. I don't know. Read another book. Yes. Well, I think the big scary question is, will there still be a startup ecosystem? Because on the one hand, you're shrinking the size of the firm. People are more leveraged. That should mean more startups, small teams can do more great, fantastic. We're definitely seeing that. I mean, people can get to 100 mil ARR.
Like not raise a B. But doing what? Selling software. Yeah. And software is getting completely commoditized. Yeah. Like all these legal guys like Harvey and whatever, like it's a good test. Like wouldn't Claude just basic mythos or fables just do a better job than something trained specifically on legal, especially with tool use. It depends because it depends on whether or not the frontier labs stay open for their best models or do they close them.
I think anyone who pays them enough, they'll find a way to be open. So if a law firm will pay them, the best result. That's not a given. It is possible for Anthropic to say like actually Fable 6. I wouldn't bet my business they're not going to enter my vertical. I think if they can enter your vertical without a custom model, they'll do it. And I think one of the better lessons here is that the general models beat the specialized ones. Yes. They don't have to enter. It's just going to be more automatic. Yeah, exactly. To opiate that market, not because the.
you know, open AI legal app, right? It's just because it's so much like why would I use something? Why would I pay $5,000 a month for some other SaaS company? I think that like 2027 will be the year of the AI harness war. Is it going to be codex? Is it going to be co-work slash cloud code? Is it going to be open claw Hermes? Like what is it? You know, who's like what harness is people going to use day to day for everything?
Yeah, right now so a lot of Silicon Valley after 2007 got to exist because you had two mobile phone providers You had you had Apple and you had Google if you had only one if you if Android didn't exist in the ecosystem would be a much tougher position for startups You would been facing a kind of a true monopolist at the end of that chain or the top of that chain
Right now, you at least have two horses fighting each other, right? So they kind of force you to behave a little bit. If it boils down to just one, it's a very bad situation for startups. Well, then they'd nationalize it and then...
Maybe we could get the government to do that. Do they really nationalize it? They didn't nationalize Google. They didn't nationalize Apple. It depends on how bad it gets. I mean, like search, it's a good utility. Like there are lots of reasons. And if you nationalize it, it might slow down and lose because now the DMV is running it and China wins. Right. It's not like the Chinese are asleep. There's an ASML machine supposedly somewhere in China now. You hear about that? Howard Litton and Collier, the ASML and was all mad because an ASML machine somehow leaked into China.
That's the lithography machine. There's only 184 of them. That's our cell forms escaping. Yeah. And then on top of it, they're developing their Huawei chips. They're working on their 7 nanometer, 5 nanometer, whatever processes. They're building their fads. They're working on it. They're not dumb. I mean, you've got 1.4.
whatever, 1.4 billion people there. They've got a lot of STEM PhDs. They have a lot of national pride. They can redirect capital. I'm not saying it matches up to innovation in a free market economy, but the US is ahead because we have created this very thin layer where we take the absolute best and brightest from all over the world and we send them like crazy to compete with each other. And then we collect the rewards from that. And Silicon Valley actually disproportionately collects the rewards and California collects the rewards. And it's not really spread out to the rest of the country as much. The rest of the country is scared shitless now.
But that's it that that's the thin blue line standing between you know the so-called free world and the Chinese competition now I'll actually take a radical point of view. I don't think we're in competition with China I Don't see the competition Taiwan. I mean every Taiwanese person I talked to doesn't want to fight You know the rich people in Taiwan are busy dodging the draft by taking their kids out of the country You know there's some some rule in Taiwan that like mandatory service mandatory conscription, but if your kid has spent
I don't know the numbers but something like three months a year for the last five years out of the country and they're not eligible for the draft anymore or no more mandatory conscription so every rich person is always taking their kids for three months a year out of the they have like a standard system doing it
They're not interested in fighting. The second largest political party there, the Kuomintang, is very pro-China. So it's already very compromised. They are... Most people in Taiwan are thinking they're gonna go like Hong Kong. They're gonna get rich in the process. They're gonna get with China and then one or two generations later they'll assimilate. And how the heck is the US gonna defend Taiwan?
like aircraft carriers are dead in land-based missiles from China can take out aircraft carriers, drones, DJI is the largest defense contractor in the world. It's like us trying to, like, it's like China trying to defend the Florida keys from us. Yeah. You know, it's ridiculous. The whole concept is ridiculous. So, and you saw we just went through with Iran. What do you think we'd run out of missiles in like seven days? We don't have the manufacturing base. Now maybe Andrew and Siranik and others get there and build all that up. But that's a long ways off.
So I mean, I think the Chinese know that and I think the Taiwanese know that and I think everyone's trying to save face while like over 10 20 years Taiwan slowly reunites with China and outside of that we don't really have a beef with China
You know, okay, Japan, whatever, you know, North Korea's got a South Korea issue, but it's not in our backyard. One of the big problems the U.S. is facing is that we've been in a low growth, high inflation environment for a while. Now maybe growth is picking back up, but so is inflation. And people are fighting over the spoils of the democratic socialist coming up, you know, the billionaire's tax, the wealth tax, the socialist trying to seize the means of production. You know, mom, Don, you're doing these rings around the democratic establishment, and they're talking about the eradication of Western civilization.
people, you gotta put food on the table, you gotta make people feel good, you gotta make people feel like they're not gonna go jobless, you gotta feed them, and
picking a war with China just seemed like the stupidest thing to do. Now we should have the appropriate tariffs against them if they have tariffs against us. If they subsidize their businesses, especially network effect or scale economies to compete with us, then we should also have our own barriers because you got to protect your local industry so it doesn't get snuffed out. So you at least have a fighting chance because these things do have economies of scale. It's not as simple as David Ricardo said where it's just like, oh yeah, I'm selling bananas and you're selling watermelons and we can just trade. No, because the guy who gets better at doing something gets really good at doing it and then can do it very, very.
cheaply or it gets a network effect around either an ecosystem or an actual lock-in where new users create value for existing users. So you can't have that simplistic mindset. You do have to play on even playing field. You have to make sure the currencies are aligned, no one's subsidizing, et cetera, et cetera. But that said, there's no reason for us to go to war with China. There really isn't. But is Taiwan like it or is it like control the South China Sea? It's like a great route. Why do we need to control the South China Sea? So like, OK, so the world breaks in half.
The world's already broken into many pieces. I know, but like right now our ships go through there and it's fine, right? But like the world literally Why would they stop our ships from going through there if they're carrying, you know trade goods back and forth like who knows? I don't want to do that. We have a rule that's like, you know what the rule of the sea is that we can freely freely pass wherever we want There is no we we have a civil war going on internally in this country in case you haven't noticed as nationalists versus communists like everyone is going more radical in both sides I mean it might be fine that the world breaks in half and China controls Asia
Right. And it's like China does sometimes they charge things and stuff like that maybe. China does control most of East Asia and to the extent that it does not it is up to Japan and South Korea and others to look out for their interests and they can ally with the US but we're not going to get into a shooting war with China over interest in the South Pacific Sea. Oh we would never do that but we will sail a ship through there and they'll hit it. Why would they hit our ship going through there?
If they run a ship to the Panama Canal, why would we attack it? If it's a legal trade vessel carrying goods and services back in the US that we're trading on. I think China actually cares way less about this stuff than we think.
China is very internally focused like the CCP's internally exactly Yeah, they they they want to stay in charge of their empire and you know I'm not a fan of communist the Communist Party although I think CCP resembles more of a capitalist fascist organization the communists is a veneer right? The fascist in the sense of like it's it's like the nation uniting for a common cause They're very good at making money. Yeah, exactly. They're actually pretty hyper competent, which actually very competent if you
compare it to like the California government. It's disastrous. It's a high IQ and homogenous. Right. Right. I mean, when you look at high speed rails, like...
guys. Yeah, they just change the people. I mean, it's time to build. It's time to build. No one's building. There's a few of us building in Silicon Valley, but we're even building ethereal things that are scary. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah, that's what they're talking about. Yeah
That's how I think of those. Yeah, exactly.
Centrist Democrat everybody Centrist Democrat Centrist Democrat Centrist Democrat Centrist Democrat San Francisco baby I feel like you're wearing it you're like please don't eat me sir Yeah, no I mean look at San Francisco like it's you know San Francisco is on the rebound We're gonna run the table on the supervisor seats at least you know like yeah, but the problem is that LA is sinking. Yes LA has sank Hollywood got chased out of LA I mean New York is insane like it's insane. Yeah, this is not a problem This is an opportunity. Oh my friend from New York are gonna come back to San Francisco. This is the problem
California has a monopoly on all the warm dry coastline all the Mediterranean land in the United States is the most powerful empire in the world So it's the most powerful as the best land in the world all in one state. There should be five or six different states 30 to 50% of the GDP of the United States will concentrate Also, but also the Arab land the beautiful coastline the good weather. It's a it's a curse of geography They've got all the natural resources, right? It's like basically southern Italy or France or even better, but in the US
It's all in one freaking state. California is this weird direct democracy thing. I mean the governor's ship for instance is not that bad. 50.1% can vote anything and they just read a headline. They're like, yeah, yeah, free cats, free food for cats and dogs for everyone. Great, we'll vote for it. Eat the rich. Steyer couldn't get in there, right? Yeah. Basically, we actually have two relatively centrist options for governor, which is good. Amazing. Which is amazing. That's great. I like that.
I think all these economist experiments will fail everywhere. Like they failed in San Francisco. They're going to fail in New York. I don't agree. I don't think they'll fail like they'll stop. The difference with San Francisco is demographics are destiny. And the demographics of New York and demographics of LA and the demographics of Chicago are just firmly committed to that cause. And the worst it gets, the more they'll vote for it. It's like Venezuela. They're going to vote all the way down.
And there is no, there is no one out there to fly and arrest the next Maduro. It has to be solved internally. United States is the last bastion for freedom. Even the COVID unlocks, the lockdowns would not have lifted if you didn't have militiamen start marching around the red states and purple states carrying M16s and AR-15s.
past the state houses being like we're done with the lockdowns, then the lockdowns came up. The whole world would have been locked down. Second member works, baby. Yeah, the whole world would be locked down for six or 12 months longer if it weren't for the 40 million intransigent Americans who have guns. And they, whether, and everybody likes to hate on them and everybody likes to shit on them, but they guard your freedom. Freedom ain't free. Yeah, freedom ain't free. You need those people out there, right? And so look, when the US, if the US were to collapse, first of all, I think freedom bleeds out from the rest of the world. You can already see what's happening on Australia and UK.
with the speech laws and the censorship and all that, and the weird arrests and so on. But if the U.S. degenerates and falls, it doesn't fail like Europe did, or even Europe isn't failing that well these days either, but it doesn't become like a big retirement home in a museum where everyone's on good social welfare for a while. It fails like a Latin American country fails because it is bordered by Latin America. So you've got a lot of people who want to get in here and they will get in here. So you're looking at much more like cartels and drugs and crime and violence and those kinds of institutions.
So okay, white pill robotics Robot, no, you're right. I don't want to do you be I we should do you be are you be ours good? I need to have universal basic robot Everyone should have a robot and the robot should cook for you pick up your shit. The good and the bad news is that the robotics The robotics boosts a bit say it's two years away the robotics skeptics say it's five to ten years away and no one thinks it's impossible Yeah, and so we already have self-driving robots self-driving cars I think you make people really happy if they have a better life
Like they aren't, you know, I mean, who likes to clean their toilet bowl? Nobody.
Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have... Unless you can have
abundance oriented. But to play, that was after a second, like healthcare. 90% of healthcare is wasted. It's not even stuff people mean. No, no, but it's like, like how much of healthcare goes into like keeping you alive for the last two weeks? Right. That's not really. I got to fix this with Markdown files, okay? Okay. But in education, there's just like a big LARP. Anyone who wants to be educated can go educate themselves right now with AI, educate themselves right now with all the open source courseware and all that stuff. They just want the stamp and they want to go to college and they want to hang out in idyllic paradise.
for four years and they want to protest for social justice and they just want to chill with their friends and party and get paid for it. It's already UBI. They said a very important thing. The college is not about
the actual act of learning. It's about like being in a room with a certain set of people who like have the right networks. Correct. It's socializing, it's babysitting, it's credentialism, there's a tiny bit of education sprinkled in for a few STEM degrees and then you go after a bunch of bullshit jobs. To legitimize it. Yeah, and then there's, yeah, all the social sciences and political science. Okay, how about this? We don't want more bullshit jobs. We want...
Dead or bullshit jobs. Okay, like I mean that's true. That's true. Yeah. Yeah, I mean why can't we just instead of like going to a cubicle Yeah, and like break your brain and do a bunch of bullshit like being an investment banker or something I think we're all gonna end up being plumbers in electricians and cutting hair
All the white collar stuff is just gonna collapse into nothing. No, no, no, no, no, no. It's making software, it's gonna collapse into nothing. No, no, no, no, no. Because it's just eating more and more. Don't you see how this is going? Everything's gonna be gone. There's a good version of this where people don't have to have just a shitty manual jobs. They can actually be handling and guiding the robots and the AIs. And so if we don't get ASI, if AI gets you to expert level but doesn't go beyond, still needs human guidance, taste and creativity,
Humans are still the motivated things in the environment. And so people become like Pokemon trainers. You're like robot handlers, right? AI handlers, and you use that to take, sorry. And that's, to be, to the truth of it, that's what we're seeing today. The people who are using AI today are more productive than ever. They are not being displaced. The only reason you're being displaced by an AI is because you refuse to use the AI. If you're using the AI, you have more work than ever. I mean, the one thing you can't replace is human desire.
Even if robots have their own desires, they cannot replace human desires So as long as humans have desires and there are AI's and robots that can help fulfill them then you always need humans in the loop and you'll always Yeah, like the moment I find out I'm talking to an AI or I'm reading the work of an AI or I'm even looking at art created by an AI I'm completely uninterested assuming it's completely done by now. No human using it Wait a second. That's just because it's shitty right now. I guarantee you it will be indistinguishable
and it will be very, very good. I don't agree. I think even if it is indistinguishable, the moment I know it's done, like for example, that's the Chinese box at that point. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But it is like, it's actually when I first saw GPT three or whatever it was, whatever was available from the API, like that was my reaction. I was like, this is a bunch of bullshit. Like this is a trick, whatever. But like.
That's not how I feel now. Like I get a lot of value day to day like hour to hour. Do you have a relationship with the AI? Do you hang out with you? Do you talk to it? Is it a friend? Getting there. Whoa. It's not my girlfriend, but. My wife is going to watch this. It's you just have someone in the Filipino call center being your girlfriend. Then it's just like filling in for the, what's the difference? What's the difference between AI and someone in the Filipino call center controlling and chatting with you?
It's a buddy of mine. Okay, don't talk to my friend. Don't talk to my friend like this. Nothing's going on between us. We're gonna end with my AI psychosis. I just think that it is actually very useful, obviously. I have a friend who is a landlord for one of these AI companies that does the AI people that you talk to.
right, like your AI girlfriend companies. And he said they had to hire extra security because these guys would show up in the middle of the night saying, where is she? Which box is she? And I want to take her home. I want to save her. Gary's having his first Black Pill moment. Oh, no. This podcast has Black Pilled Me. By the way, this entire podcast was AI generated. No one was actually here. We deny everything.